Okay, so let's talk about some of the
roles then on a project.
Okay, so we're going to
be talking about roles for a
predictive project and then
roles on an agile project.
Alright, so we'll talk about predictive
projects first.
So on a predictive project, you have a
project manager.
So project manager,
they are accountable for all
the work that needs to
be done on the project.
They're accountable, responsible for the
team.
they plan the work and then they delegate
the work to the team so they are managing
and coordinating the entire work all of
the work from beginning to the end
throughout the entire project they're
accountable for everything and one of the
key things is they are delegating they're
planning the work then they're delegating
to appropriate team members and team
members are essentially reporting to the
project manager during that project The
project manager then is ensuring,
making sure all the work is getting done.
They're the ones that are also looking at
the metrics of the project.
We head a schedule, behind schedule, over
budget, under budget,
and so on and so forth.
So they're seeing how our project is
progressing, you know, compared to the plan.
Another role then is the business analyst.
So business analyst is one of the team
members typically on a predictive project.
And one of the
responsibilities then of the
business analyst is
collecting requirements.
It's understanding the requirements,
defining the requirements,
working with the customer
to collect requirements.
So business analysts has knowledge about
the business and the customer.
They work with the customer to collect
their requirements.
They're almost like a
go-between, between the customer,
between the business,
between the technical teams.
So business analysts need to be able to
communicate, right?
at all levels.
So just as a high-level general
difference, a business analyst defines
what the deliverable will be,
whereas a project manager
is going to define how to
achieve that deliverable.
So the business analysts will collect the
requirements.
They'll tell them, all right, these are
the requirements.
The project manager then is going to
decide, all right, how are we going to
convert these requirements into a
deliverable?
Okay.
Now, other roles then on a predictive
project?
The project team, actually, for a project
team.
So the project team basically is everybody
involved on the project.
So they are responsible then for
performing the work.
So the project manager is going to be
working with the team.
The project team are also subject matter
experts as well.
So remember, the project manager is not
necessarily a technical expert.
The project manager is someone that can
get things moving along.
The project manager has communication
skills.
The project manager is somebody that can
get teams working together.
The project team are the ones that's
actually physically performing the work.
So the work with the project manager to
plan the work, then they will be executing
the work, delivering the actual work
product itself.
And they are, essentially,
essentially for the purpose
of the project, they're
reporting to the project manager.
Now, the project team, though,
also includes, right?
It's not just individual team members.
So it's not just the individual team
that's performed with the work.
It is them, but it also includes the
project manager, the management group,
if they're part of the project,
the project leadership team, key
stakeholders that have sign off
responsibility.
So let's talk about the project leadership
team then on this
next bullet point, right?
So another role on a project, on a
predictive project, is the project
management team, also known as the project
leadership team.
And as the name suggests, they provide
leadership for the project.
They're the ones that are signing off on
the deliverables.
They're the ones that's given the initial
direction of the project.
They're the ones
that's saying this is what
the project is about
and so on and so forth.
The RIS subset of the project team,
as the project team includes the project
management team, and the project
management team then, they are there to
make strategic decisions about the
project.
Now, in an agile environment, in an agile
environment, one of the
roles is the product owner.
And the product owner represents,
if you like, the voice of the customer.
The product owner represents the customer.
The customer is giving requirements.
The product owner is making sure those
requirements then are going to be delivered.
So they're the ones then, once those
requirements, once they've collected the
requirements, remember
in an agile environment
group, the requirements
are known as user stories.
So they're collecting user stories.
They're working with the team, with the
agile team as well,
collect the user stories.
But the product owner
is going to be prioritizing
those user stories to
create the product backlog.
That's their responsibility.
Again, they're going to be working with
the team, right?
They don't, the product owner doesn't just
do it by him or herself.
They work with the team as well,
right?
But they are responsible then for
prioritizing these backlog items.
And they represent the, they represent the
customer.
Now also, the ultimate
accountability for all of the work
on the project actually
falls with the product owner.
The product owner has the ultimate
accountability, right,
on an on an agile project.
The project team is going to be performing
all of the work, but the product owner is
the one that's going to be signing off on
all of the work.
The product owner is going to be
determining this product or this,
you know, whatever the
team is delivering at the end
of the sprint, is this meeting
our definition of done?
It's a product owner that's signing off on
that.
So they actually have the ultimate
accountability.
As far as the customer is
concerned, they have the
ultimate accountability for
the work that is delivered.
The team facilitator,
the team facilitator is the
closest thing to the
quote-unquote project manager.
In a predictive environment,
the project manager
is the command and
control project manager.
or they are known as a command and control
project manager.
They are responsible.
They are accountable for all the work that
goes on in the project.
They are responsible for
the planning and the executing
and the monitoring controlling
and so on and so forth.
The team facilitator, though, is a servant
leader.
They are known as a servant leader.
As a servant leader, they are there to
basically collaborate.
One of the key things is collaboration.
they collaborate with the
team to make sure work is
getting done, to make sure
things are moving along, right?
And that's one of the key, one of the key
things there regarding the team
facilitator, they are in a collaborative,
right?
So a team facilitator does not delegate
any work.
The team themselves are the ones that are
determining what work needs to be done.
In a predictive environment, the project
manager delegates the work, but in an
agile environment, the team facilitator
does not delegate any work.
It's a team that's determining the work
that needs to be done.
The team facilitator is making sure that
happens.
So the team facilitator is
making sure then that the
team has all of the tools
necessary to do their work.
They've got everything at their disposal.
They need additional data, they need
information.
They have the information.
They need certain tools, they have those
appropriate tools.
So the team facilitators
making sure that the team has all
the necessary items for the
team to actually perform the work.
And they are there to remove any
obstacles, any impediments.
So anything that's slowing
down the team, the team
facilitator is going to
be taking care of that.
So just as a simple example, let's say,
you know, beginning of a sprint,
senior management, decide, you know,
to, or senior, management approach one of
the team members and
ask them to run daily status
reports, or can you just
run these reports for us?
And these reports are taking time out of
their sprint.
So that's an impediment.
That's an impediment to the work of the
team.
So the team facilitator then will be
taking care of that.
So either the team facilitator will be
running the report themselves, right?
Or, you know, they can negotiate with the
stakeholder.
Do you really need these
reports and how often
do you need these reports
and so on and so forth?
But it's a team facilitator
then that will be removing
that impediment from that
particular team member.
So again, don't ever, ever get this
confused on the exam.
The project manager can delegate the work.
Team facilitator in an agile project never
delegates.
Work is not.
delegated on an Agile project.
Again, you know, these are scenarios you
have to look out for on the PMP exam.
Then the Agile team, right?
So the Agile team,
they're the ones that are
responsible for performing
the work during the sprint.
They are the ones that are going to be
determining the size of the work,
the level of effort.
So they're going to be doing the relative
estimating of all of the work.
During each sprint, they're going to
prioritize the user stories Now,
the Agile team, though, are made up of
developers, designers, testers.
The Agile team are not just developers.
Agile team are, you know, there's going to
be several people on Agile team,
right, several roles.
The Agile team themselves are small.
They're generally small teams.
But they're going to be made up of
developers, business analysts,
testers, designers, and so on and so
forth.
Plus, you know, any other additional role.
and they are known as a generalizing
specialists.
We're going to be talking about T-shaped
skills in one of our videos.
And T-shaped skill basically means then
that you have detailed knowledge of one
particular area, detail
skills, but then you
can spread your skills
across several areas.
So that's what a generalizing specialist
is.
And so the agile team is going to be made
up of these generalizing specialists.
And then you have the Agile Coach.
Now, the Agile Coach is an optional.
It's an optional role in an Agile Project.
And as a name suggests, they are there to
coach and train the team.
They could be internal to the
organization.
They could be external or internal to the
project or external to the project.
A lot of times, the actual team
facilitator will work as the Agile Coach.
But if it's an inexperienced team
facilitator, inexperience meaning,
I mean, they obviously have had to have an
of an Agile project in order to be a team
facilitator, but they may not have been a
team facilitator for a long time,
in which case then they may bring in an
Agile coach, a separate agile coach.
But as I said, the Agile Coach is an
optional role, but they are there
essentially to coach and train the Agile
team.
Now, just a couple of additional roles I
want to mention, the project sponsor.
Sponsor is for both the Agile project as
well as a predictive project.
the main purpose of the project sponsor is
to provide funding for the project.
They're going to be providing funding for
the project.
And they also sign off on the project
charter.
Remember, the project charter is a formal
authorization for the project to begin.
And the sponsor then is going to be
signing off on the project charter.
And then another role that I just want to
mention is the functional manager.
Now, the functional manager is not really
a role on a project, right?
In many organizations, especially matrix
organizations, team members report to a
functional manager, but then they may be
working on one or two additional projects.
This mostly happens in a predictive, so
we're mostly talking about predictive here.
So the functional manager then,
although they're not part of the project
team or really anything to
do with the project per se,
but they're the ones that
are providing those resources.
They're the ones that are providing the
team members.
So on a predictive project, right,
you're in a matrix organization,
you're the project manager, you're the
command and control project manager.
Where are your team coming from?
They might be coming from different areas
of the organization.
Those team members are reporting to a
functional manager.
Those functional managers are releasing
those team members to work on your project.
So they're going to be
approving the work, or
rather they're going to be
approving their response.
responsibilities, they're
going to be approving,
their start date and end
dates on your project.
Right, what date they're going to be
rolling onto your project, what date
they're going to be rolling off on your
project.
So these are just some
of these significant roles
that you need to know about
for the PMP exam, right?
And we will be talking about all of these
roles in future videos as well,
in subsequent videos.